[Music]
okay the next
example is the one about which this
picture will be
useful let's consider the
following Square diagam and that's going
to be really the most challenging so far
I'm going
to identify this edge with this sted
like this so far so good if I identify
this Ed with this sted like this we get
a Taurus thank you but I'm going to now
reverse the orientation like this what
on Earth is this going to
become okay
first let's identify the easy dig the
vertical edges then I get this
cylinder where the verticle has been
identified with the difference that the
top and the Bottom now have opposite
circulations okay and then we have to do
the identification but now you remember
before when we discussed the Taurus I
took this p part and then stretched it
and put it like that this time I cannot
do this because if I put it like that
the circulations will be the opposite so
I have to do something very strange you
see if I bring it over
here like this then it looks like the
circulations are in the right direction
but then you see I cannot put
this against this like
this because if I do this I have to go
through the
surface it's impossible in a
threedimensional
space but that's okay let's relax it's
impossible in 3D but it's possible in
higher dimensional spaces as we shall
see right in the course so we shall cut
across the surface anyway self
intersection let's say that surface is
made of magic material and I I can walk
straight through
and come straight
out and then what we get is this very
interesting surface which I should draw
like this because it's impossible to
draw coherently in three dimensional
space can you get the feeling for this
surface this surface is the famous Klein
bottle Felix Klein was a a very
influential German mathematician towards
the end of the 19th century and it's
called the clim
bottle in symbolic terms this
identification is very easy because you
get this
Square the vertical identifications as
before 0 Y is identified with one y
That's
okay this time however x0 is identified
with what do you think it's identified
with 1 - x time you not X - 1 the
opposite of X is not X - 1 but 1 - x
opposite of because I'm measuring from 1
measuring from zero anyways so this is
for so that is orientation reversing
that's orientation preserving and if you
do that you get the climo so result of
this quotient the quotient space of the
square by those equivalence relations or
those identifications is the climent
bottle now this is what we called a self
intersecting picture because it cuts the
bottle cuts through its own surface but
as I said we're using magic material so
that's
okay there's so much magic in this room
that I lost the
Eraser ah here it is
okay
now things get interesting what happens
if I cut that clim of
[Applause]
in its plane of
symmetry this
[Applause]
CL in
halves let me draw a picture and explain
what I'm doing is like this again
there's a somebody who's about to
cut but he looks a little more worried
than
before because he's cutting something
that's nonorientable it turns
out who's going who can guess what's
going to happen so this is what it is
in
mining you see a Taurus looked like this
you take a circle and you just sweep it
out like that and like that is that okay
can you see can you visualize this
that's a Taurus clim bottle is funnier
so you take a circle and you sweep out a
tube but now the tube doesn't come back
from the top it comes back from the
bottom and cuts across the surface and
then joins up to this so at the top
there is sort of a surface like this
yeah Rim like this and on the outside
the cube goes down
on the inside the surface like becomes a
little narrower and then comes out and
then joins to the alter
surface can you see this I hope you can
so that's the
um
climbable now please see the
picture on the
hand it shows on the top of
the picture are
climb but on lying on the
side yeah horizontally position and if
you slice
it through the plane of
symmetry you can open it up in two and
that's the picture that you
get and do you notice that there is a
funny self self intersection as the
surface goes like that and then joins up
it cuts through itself but let's not
worry about this cut
let's actually lift it and it turns out
that what you
get
is two
copies of before we used to write a draw
there we got two copies of ordinary
strips this time you get two copies of
yes you've guessed it movie strips
that's right
so if you glue two movie strips together
you get the client botle if you glue two
ordinary strips together you get the
Taurus let's see how
that really works we can check this
statement
by A New Concept for us by calculating
with pictures I'm sure you have all
calculated with numbers you have
calculated with formulas but we shall
now calculate with pictures
in the
following
wa take this original diagram like that
and like that and like that and like
that now let's introduce a
cut like this I'm going to cut it along
this curve and then we
get this picture
and this
picture
agreed so this Edge must be identified
with this Edge at the end and this edge
with this Edge but because we cut it in
two at the end we have to glue back the
cut so let's denote this cut by this and
this so those two cuts must be
identified at the end okay now this
becomes very
easy I can straighten this up because
we're doing topology everything is
soft I don't care about those two things
and then you get wait a minute am I
doing the right thing I'm doing the
wrong thing am I
not just one
second ah excuse me I didn't I don't
want to cut it like this I'm going to
cut it in a different fashion I'm
terribly
sorry so I'm going to cut it because I'm
cutting it like this sorry about this
so I have that and that okay
so I'm going to cut it vertically
because I'm slicing it vertically and
I'm going to go along this
cut okay scissors like this but when I
arrive at this point this point is
identified with this
point so I keep going do you remember
what we did when we cut the movie strip
it's a bit similar to this and then when
I finish cutting here this point is the
same as the initial point so that's the
cut
okay so what happens if I do this cut
well this consists of two parts the
middle part is very
easy he looks like
this and this is like that and this is
like that okay and we have to somehow
identify those edges so
um we'll worry about that
later and after for the other one you
have to have
this
cut and this
cut
and this Edge should be identified with
this
Edge is that okay because this part
should be identified with this part and
this part with this part is that okay
because this should be identified with
this so I'm going to indicate this by
introducing a new set of arrows like
this and like this and on the side
there's no problem like that like like
that okay so that's the cut
picture but at the same time if I glue
these things together let's put it over
here so this is equal to if I identify
this with with this Edge you get the
following picture so this has been
identified in the middle and on this
side there's a cut on this side is cut
and then here I have to be careful I
moved it over here so I get the double
arrow here and single Arrow here and I
move it over here so single Arrow here
and double arrow
here you see that yes but what is this
look that if you look at this strip I
have to identify the edge edges like
this that's a movie strip
how about this this side should be
identified with this side another mve
is so we have the result that the clim
bottle a clim bottle is obtained by
by gluing
together
gluing yeah
[Applause]
glue two movie
strips
along the boundaries so
[Applause]
course difficult
to um visualize but let's try to draw
the picture this way that's a movie
strip y another movie
strip and we'd like to glue those two
things together
before when we had the ordinary strip
and ordinary strip we glue them together
we got we obtain the Taurus that was
easy to visualize this is rather
harder but if you think differently it's
not so difficult either because you see
the boundary of this movie strip is just
a single Circle boundary of this movie
strip is another single Circle and I'm
just gluing them together that's what
I'm doing you cannot do this without
self
intersection inside uh three dimensional
space but you can do it if you use magic
material this
example the fact that mov strip mov
strip together give you a cim bottle and
cim bottle cut in half becomes two mov
strips will be
useful will be used
later in the
theory of
surgery later by surgery I don't mean
medical surgery but there's some
similarity you are cutting and pasting
and so forth you're doing all sorts of
violence to
manifolds
okay
good so this is enough for today